<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Zack Batist</title>
<link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://zackbatist.info/old-posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A trove of older blog posts from when I was much younger, less experienced, and cringe as fuck.
</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Blog for Week 11 - Natural Places and the Nature / Culture Divide</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-21-blog-for-week-11-natural-places-and-the-nature-culture-divide.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>The articles that I read this week dealt with the impact of the physical landscape on human behaviour and associated&nbsp;material manifestations. I started by reading Ingold’s (1996) book chapter, which was primarily concerned with the dissolution of the oft-conceived nature/culture divide. Ingold attempted to portray&nbsp;humans as entities&nbsp;embedded within the same fabric as what is often termed “natural” or “environmental”. In particular, he focuses his attention towards contemporary views of hunter-gatherer groups. Ingold offers alternative views of the roles of three hunter-gatherer groups,&nbsp;by viewing the management of nature less as economic or subsistence oriented behaviour but rather through the lens of social or spiritual&nbsp;perspectives. Instead of understanding&nbsp;hunting and gathering as behaviour guided by principles of optimization/maximization/minimization,&nbsp;which tend to distinguish humans as consumers of nature and hence as&nbsp;distinct from the natural world, Ingold suggests that the utilization of certain natural resources is&nbsp;embedded within social worldviews that are not as strongly oriented towards&nbsp;this aspect of human exceptionalism.</p>
<p>Although Ingold did not explicitly recognize the agency of the environment and non-human organisms (he did acknowledge that they do possess agency, but rather broadly), these ideas were picked up by Bauer (2014) and Bradley (2000). Bauer showed how the landscape could explicitly shape human activities and alter the social fabric of humans. More specifically, he&nbsp;notes that certain geological formations allowed for individuals at particular&nbsp;locations to construct monuments alongside quarries that were already being mined, whereas this was not possible in other areas. In this way, it is understood that geological processes effect how places imbued with special meaning were constructed. Similarly, Bradley looked at the places where metal artefacts were found in sacrificial contexts,&nbsp;in order to reconstruct the worldviews of those who engaged in relationships with naturalistic deities.</p>
<p>The work of Bauer and Bradley gave me more&nbsp;things to think about. Bauer was very concerned with the ascription of agency to the landscape, and this prompted me to reassess what is capable of possessing agency, and whether the definition of agency should be expanded. He sites Latour (2005:71), whose broad definition of an agent&nbsp;encompasses “any thing that does modify a state of affairs by making a difference”. I was a bit reserved to accept this definition since, from a perspective that emphasizes complexity theory, non-linear causation and chaos theory, virtually anything could possess agency. This ultimately devalues the term. Moreover, it is difficult for me to wrap my head around the ascription of agency to broad-scale entities such as geological formations. I am more prone to accept as agents things&nbsp;that humans interact with on a day-to-day basis on a comparable scale, such as&nbsp;buildings and moveable objects; however&nbsp;geological “things” exist/occur at vastly different orders of magnitude. It is true that we enact culture in a particular environment that influences our behaviours to some degree, but when all is said and done it is the current state of the environment as sensed through our senses (which changes from moment to moment) that effects how I will act. In other words, the&nbsp;fact that the earth formed throughout&nbsp;billions of years does not impact my actions, however the current environment, which exists as a result of previous natural activity, does.</p>
<p>Bradley’s work seems to be more agreeable in this sense, since what he terms “natural places” are actually&nbsp;ascribed agency by the people who attend to them. They are noticeable contemporary features of the landscape, and are consistently&nbsp;part of contemporary consideration. Bauer’s work reminded me of discussions concerning the development of agriculture in the Levant as a potential&nbsp;response to the Younger Dryas climatic fluctuation, which has been&nbsp;criticized by many (but certainly not by everyone) for&nbsp;its environmental&nbsp;deterministic tendencies. It is also reminiscent of discussions concerning global warming and climate change today, which is nearly imperceivable due to the long term effects of the associated&nbsp;phenomena. In a way, one key strategy&nbsp;of environmental movements is getting people to recognize the effects that global warming has or will have on peoples’ day-to-day lives; or in other words, to get people to recognize the agency of “mother earth”.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-21-blog-for-week-11-natural-places-and-the-nature-culture-divide.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blog for Week 10 - Landscapes of Movement: Roads &amp; Pilgrimmage</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-15-blog-for-week-10-landscapes-of-movement-roads-pilgrimmage.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Since I missed a few classes last semester due to intensive thesis work, I did not engage in class discussions regarding certain sets of readings. If anyone from class is still receiving updates, feel free to leave comments. This first post corresponds with Week 10 in the syllabus:&nbsp;<em>Landscapes of Movement: Roads &amp; Pilgrimmage</em>, and the papers are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ardren, Traci and Justin Lowry (2011): The Travels of Maya Merchants in the Ninth And Tenth Centuries AD: Investigations at Xuenkal and the Greater Cupul Province, Yucatan, Mexico. World Archaeology 43(3):428-443.</li>
<li>Sorge, Antonio and Roddick, Andrew P. (2012) Mobile Humanity: The Delocalization of Anthropological Research. Reviews in Anthropolog 41(4): 273-301.</li>
<li>Ur, Jason A (2009) Emergent landscapes of movement in early Bronze Age northern Mesopotamia. In Snead, J.E.. Erickson C.L. and Darling J.A. (Eds.) Landscapes of Movement: Paths, Trails, and Roads in Anthropological Perspective, pp.&nbsp;180- 203. University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia.</li>
</ul>
<p>Ardren and Lowry examined the physical geography, as modified through human activity (i.e.&nbsp;the construction of cities, settlements and monuments), and modelled the movements of a merchant bringing goods from the&nbsp;coast of the Gulf of Mexico to Chichen Itza, a major Mayan capital city. Their aim was to reconstruct the travels of Mayan traders, and their work seems to have consisted of&nbsp;tracing merchants’ likely itineraries (including likely routes taken and their corresponding timing), and comparison of&nbsp;the observable archaeological record with their presumed behaviours. What is interesting about this paper is how the authors attempted to account for the limitations and motivations experienced and considered by a merchant — by imagining these factors from a first&nbsp;person perspective. I do note some limitations, however. First of all, it is presumed that all merchants had the same motivations and experiences. This renders the agentic aspect of the first person perspective completely moot, since the discussion is reoriented towards the examination of mercantile behaviour as an institution rather than as collective activities. Additionally, the authors presume that a&nbsp;trader’s primary goal was to reach Chichen Itza from Isla Cerritos along a direct and optimized trajectory. The mapped trajectory makes sense within the bounded survey region, but there may have also been other potentially rewarding target markets to visit outside of this arbitrarily defined tract. The authors also presume that each merchant was acting in a freelance and competitive manner, and were guided by rewards offered by buyers in the capital. Must large monumental mounds necessarily represent gravitational centres? Essentially, I find that the authors take on the sensory perspective of the trader, and yet primarily consider&nbsp;the&nbsp;motivations of elites situated in the capital. Alternatively, there may have been more value for merchants in maintaining cooperative relationships with other traders inhabiting the region, as well as with the inhabitants of settlements surrounding the capital. Their familiarity with the environments that they traversed suggests that&nbsp;merchants were locals to the area,&nbsp;and that the distributions of artefacts originating from the coastal ports may not have been the result of explicit mercantile behaviour, but as a buildup of social relationships (i.e.&nbsp;relationships that are not explicitly defined in economic terms) among members of various inland communities.</p>
<p>Ur’s paper seems to be more straightforward. The author identified trails left behind through repetitive and concentrated activity, and interpreted their orientations as the routes between fields that cattle herders would follow before arriving at open grazing areas. Since farmers used tracts of land located just outside the city, the movements of cattle had to be guided between fields in order to avoid trampling on crops. The points where the trails end thus demarcate borders of fields, where cattle then spread out to pasture. Ur notes that these borders can be used to estimate population densities and to better&nbsp;understand the subsistence economy&nbsp;in this archaeological setting. This seems like a very solid study, and the vast number of sites exhibiting these trails poses interesting potential for comparison among them. However there is still the risk of&nbsp;generalizing&nbsp;the local economies at each site when conducting such multi-site studies, and it&nbsp;is important to recognize variability through assessment of each&nbsp;site as a whole before drawing comparisons among them.</p>
<p>As Sorge and Roddick point out,&nbsp;it is quite difficult to recognize peoples’ individuality when looking towards the deep past. I also imagine that it would be&nbsp;difficult to broaden ones’ understanding of a person and generalize their behaviour among&nbsp;others in his or her&nbsp;community. At what point is it acceptable or not acceptable&nbsp;to ascribe highly similar motivations and behaviours&nbsp;to unacknowledged members of a community based upon focused observations of a single member, and vice versa regarding the characterization of an individual based upon an understanding of collective action? In multi-site analysis this assumption that “sites” equal their inhabitants is extremely prevalent. In an ideal world,&nbsp;dynamic processes within sites should be considered to a greater extent when examining interactions between them. However this may also be very impractical. Assuming that a common goal of multi-site studies is to reconstruct past behaviours, it may be downright impossible, since any such model can never reach perfect resolution relative to the archaeological phenomena being examined.</p>
<p>One other striking note&nbsp;I made, perhaps while implicitly comparing the work of Ardren and Lowry (2011) and Ur (2009), is that&nbsp;the&nbsp;landscape itself should not be the focus of study. Instead, I believe that it might be better to evaluate how people physically coped with, altered, or interacted with the landscape as a material. This latter approach is better poised to reconstruct human behaviours and the rationales behind them based upon&nbsp;assessments grounded in physical evidence, rather than attempts of&nbsp;estimating&nbsp;the perceptions of generalized individuals through largely cognitive assessments. I believe&nbsp;that this point is illustrated in other work discussed&nbsp;throughout this class as well; for instance,&nbsp;Joyce’s (2004) and Pauketat and Alt’s (2005)&nbsp;applications of historical processualism are&nbsp;exemplary of the former approach, and&nbsp;Van Dyke’s (2008) and Fowles’ (2009) phenomenological observations pertain&nbsp;to the latter. Whereas Ur (2009) was concerned with the physical transformation of the landscape in response to human activities, Ardren and Lowry’s&nbsp;(2011) work&nbsp;was based upon presumed understandings of ways by which&nbsp;environments were perceived by those exhibiting generalized and easily predictable&nbsp;behaviour, and how these perceived landscapes might have influenced peoples’ behaviour.</p>
<section id="comments" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments">Comments</h4>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Hi Zack, Three quick (if broad) questions: Assuming that a common goal of multi-site studies is to reconstruct past behaviours… What is the common goal? Could you extract that from our (sometimes convoluted!) discussion? Was Ur’s paper straightforward? Certainly his method was, but I wonder if his actual approach was. I thought this was a rather elegant analysis. Is he simply looking at the physical response to human activities? Doesn’t he include some phenomenological aspects of the rulers movements through the landscape as well?</p>
<p><strong>Zack:</strong> I agree that Ur’s paper was elegant, and his commentary on the imposition of certain behaviours relating to inter-settlement travel from the bottom-up was especially interesting. The responses to the physical landscape are what stood out to me since this seems like the most practical way of conducting landscape archaeology in prehistoric contexts. I think that Ur’s evocation of the travelling elite definitely serves to reinforce a particular view of socio-politics in this setting, however it is reliant on certain assumptions gained from textual sources that are not readily available in most other prehistoric archaeological contexts.</p>
<p>I guess the goals of archaeologists conducting multi-sited studies differ according to their research questions. Ur’s goal was to leverage the northern Mesopotamian trail system in order to better understand the roles of elites and of commoners in that society. Ardren and Lowry aimed to re-model past economic processes by predicting “common sense” behaviours. Ardren and Lowry had a pre-conceived idea of the role of the merchant in society, and this conception guided their dataset and analysis from the top-down. On the other hand, Ur depicted a way of better understanding social issues by re-imagining peoples’ experiences. Although Ur’s study was more so based on a bottom-up approach, he was still constructing a model; whereas the features of his model (imagined experiences, phenomenology) are largely grounded in theory, whereas Ardren and Lowry used distance and artefact counts instead. In this sense, the problems of generalization and presumption persists. However I do see that it is relatively simple and easy to reconstruct certain generalized behaviours based on physical geography, but that it is often much more fulfilling to assess peoples’ experiences and relationships through application of social theory.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-15-blog-for-week-10-landscapes-of-movement-roads-pilgrimmage.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SP&amp;L intro draft, and some other thoughts</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-02-spl-intro-draft-and-some-other-thoughts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>I’ve been doing lots of reading in preparation for&nbsp;my Space, Place and Landscape Paper while on vacation. One book in particular really had&nbsp;a large impact, Timothy Pauketat’s <em>Chiefdoms and Other Archaeological Delusions</em> (2007). It is a fantastic synthesis of historical processualism that doesn’t get too bogged down with citation chains or jargon, and was extremely relatable. It definitely got me to&nbsp;think about practice theory in a more practical way. I followed up by re-reading many key articles concerning the emergence of the Halaf and how it is defined, all with a renewed perspective that solidified how I want to tackle this paper. I wrote a short draft for my&nbsp;introduction, which more realistically outlines its aims. I also think that the structure outlined in a previous post will be modified by merging&nbsp;the overview concerning&nbsp;“what the Halaf?” with&nbsp;the section on common assumptions and problems. This introduction (with more meat added to it, perhaps) will precede that section:</p>
<p>In archaeology pertaining to the prehistory of southwest Asia and Anatolia, the Halaf is commonly referred to as a cultural identity, a geographical expanse, a chronological period, and a specific form of material culture. As Stuart Campbell (1999) has pointed out, the true meaning of the Halaf has been mis-conceptualized ever since the initial identification of Halaf-style pottery in 1911 (Von Oppenheimer?) at the eponymous Tell Halaf type-site. The Halaf as a cultural identity has persistently been referred to as a physical entity that occupied space and time, and physically manifested on maps as the area between concretely delineated cultural borders. Realistically however, such references seem to be based upon a foundation laid down during the early 20th century that does not adequately represent past realities (Campbell 1999). Moreover, any discussion concerning the ways in which the Halaf emerged from prior cultural contexts defined in similar ways, or of other regionally oriented trends developed under a similar framework, will only work to refine this extended construct. In order to more effectively understand past realities, it is necessary to decouple the available data from the aforementioned restrictive and top-down framework. Instead, the archaeological data should be situated within a social perspective that captures its role within the formation of community identities, and use such interpretations to derive conclusions concerning broader scale interactions or delimitations. Moreover, it is important to maintain a heterarchical perspective that allows for the nature of a social system (e.g.&nbsp;power relationships, clusters of shared identity, etc.) to be understood as the result of the distributed and collective agency of all members of society.</p>
<p>The aim of this paper is to characterize the Halaf from a renewed social perspective through a reassessment of regional models and an analysis of obsidian circulation networks. More specifically, a practice theoretic approach will be taken to evaluate the variability of material culture across northern Mesopotamia and the northern Levant regions during the 6th millennium B.C., with a particular focus on the ways by which obsidian was procured, worked and used. Although similar work has been conducted quite recently (cf.&nbsp;Campbell 2000:21-22; Campbell and Healey 2013; Healey 2007; Healey and Campbell 2014), here I hope to more explicitly relate the principles of practice theory as derived from Pauketat (2007), Pauketat and Alt (2005) and Joyce (2004), who emphasize the formation of political economies in their work –– a topic that lies at the heart of discussion surrounding the nature of the Halaf.</p>
<p>I also started the next section, and I’m going at a slower yet more thoughtful pace. I’m trying to be more strategic in my writing, but sometimes it seems that I’m overthinking or over-interpreting things. I also may need to expand my reading base concerning overviews of&nbsp;the Halaf, since I find myself relying on a handful of sources. They are quite authoritative and are cited often, but I think this is creating a bit of an&nbsp;echo chamber effect.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2015-01-02-spl-intro-draft-and-some-other-thoughts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outline for SP&amp;L paper</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-12-18-outline-of-spl-paper.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p><strong>Main topic:</strong> How can a practice-oriented approach be useful for determining the ways by which the Halaf emerged, and for evaluating the distribution of its recognizable material manifestations? . <strong>Intro:</strong> What is the Halaf? What is the Burnt House at Arpachiyah? What are the primary concerns of archaeologists studying these contexts? Introduce the main question: How can a practice-oriented approach be useful for determining the ways by which the Halaf emerged, and for evaluating the distribution of its recognizable material manifestations? What are the assumptions of scholars writing about this? Preference for work at broader (regional and supra-regional) scales. Agency often completely ignored, and replaced with reference to Barth (1969) or similar explanations for cultural contact or change. At other times, the effects of agency are not viewed as transferable to broader scales, and tend to be compartmentalized to intra-site evaluations (examples…). Looking at end products, not process or practice. Lack of phenomenological or embodiment approach (van Dyke vs Chataigner and Barge?). Always reverting to core/periphery model despite constant reminders to consider the role of nomads, to consider actions of individuals first and foremost in the construction of society rather than the other way around.</p>
<p>What are Joyce and Pauketat thinking? How does this relate to space, place and political economy? Through collective action, individuals build society and decide how it is governed. These actions, which effect the larger world around them, are manifested in the archaeological record in terms of practices, rather than end products. Products/consumption may also be considered, but primarily in terms of how they allow one to experience the world through their senses (phenomenology) or through other aspects of their bodies (embodiment). The meanings that people ascribed to places (raw material sources, natural environments, artificial structures, etc) may be deduced through examination of their behaviours and practices, as read through the material culture. These interpretations may supplement or redirect our understanding of socio-economic/political ways of life. If mapping or refining cultural boundaries is indeed the main goal, then this information must be mapped or visualized in an appropriate way — highlighting different kinds of sites, kinds of interactions between them, and processes of raw material procurement or whatnot.</p>
<p><strong>Move to the data:</strong> How do these approaches (Joyce and Pauketat) relate to this specific context? The re-examinations of the material from the burnt house at Arpachiya by Healey and Campbell make further interpretations of the same material easier. Such re-interpretations would incorporate practice-oriented perspectives to some significant classes of material. Obsidian will be the main material considered, but painted pottery may also be interesting to examine. However my experience with work relating to pottery may make this difficult, and I would have to rely on the prior work of others. The burning of the Burnt House will also be crucial to evaluate from an agent-based and practice-oriented approach, but I’m unsure about how to situate this in the paper.</p>
<p><strong>Network analysis:</strong> Dataset will include all sites in the “zone of Halaf influence”, including those with only 1 artefact. Might have to look at the sourcing studies for each of these sites to see if finer chronological resolution may be attained. One-mode network of sites connected to sites via similar proportions of raw material (just like thesis work). One-mode with flipped node/edges so that strong similarities are nodes connected by sites represented as edges — used to highlight sites as meeting points or borders à la Crumley and Marquadt 1988. Two-mode network (two “classes” of nodes: sites and obsidian sources), with sites connected to sources (must figure out a weighting mechanism), and its one-mode derivative whereby sources are connected to other sources via sites who use each’s material — this latter networks used to determine groups of sources that are commonly used together. The different ways in which these materials were used can then be added to discussion, and visualized accordingly by colourizing certain edges to highlight what kind of interactions they may represent, or to denote relationships among sites based upon other forms of evidence like pottery variation, use of seal stamps, etc. Final map would look something like those drawn up by Delerue (2007) in her dissertation, but hopefully relating more to inter-relationships between sites, rather than between sites and sources.</p>
<section id="comments." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments.">Comments.</h4>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Hi Zack, A couple of quick thoughts: Instead of “What are Joyce and Pauketat thinking? How does this relate to space, place and political economy?” I would suggest you consider a questions like, “How might a practice-based approach help with thinking about the emergence of new political and economic systems?” This is because it may push you to read a bit more broadly on what this approach is about — you may want to look, for instance, at a very famous article by Sherry Ortner “theory in anthropology since the sixties” which includes a section on theories of practice. You have lots of data included here. This paper should be no longer than 25 pages… plan accordingly.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-12-18-outline-of-spl-paper.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Notes on paper for Space, Place and Landscape — on the role of Arpachiyah and the socio-economic landscape of the Halaf</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-12-11-notes-on-the-role-of-arpachiyah-and-the-socio-economic-landscape-of-the-halaf.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Halaf suddenly arose and spread across a large area — between 5200 and 4500 BCE (7200 - 6500 BP) Simple band around the rim is standard ceramic ware, but more complex designs as well, up to 3 colour Architecture differed as well — round houses with domed our flat roofs, as opposed to rectangular houses earlier and later. Rectangular architecture used in “secondary buildings” according to Campbell (1992). Emerged from the Hassuna, which was distributed across northern Syria and Iraq, more or less at the same time at each locale. This suggests that “the spread of a single cultural tradition over much of the northern portion of the Near East can no longer be dated to a time late in the Halaf, perhaps about 4700 B.C.E.,but must be placed much earlier, at the end of the Hassuna, around 5200 B.C.E.” (Campbell 1992: 183). The Halaf seems to have arose with the aid of already established social “infrastructure” that spanned a wide region, and it’s specific origin point can therefore not be deduced. The Halaf occurs during the mid-point between the beginnings of agriculture and the rise of the first cities, so is a natural place to look for the processes that led from one to the other. Large increase in population from the early Halaf to the late, due to the intensification of agriculture in northern Iraq and Syria. Davidson 1981 and Davidson and McKerrall 1980 have conducted NAA on Halaf pottery and found that it was probably manufactured in only a few locations, and traded elsewhere. Perhaps this ties in with LeBlanc and Watson 1973, who found variations of Halaf motifs correspond with distance. Obsidian is found in large quantities in northern Iraq and Syria despite the long distance to eastern Anatolian sources. Obsidian is found mainly as finished blades, suggesting that it was worked elsewhere and that contacts with these producers was stable and and consistent. No indication from Campbell 1992 regarding the specific sources of these blades. “With a single exception, none of the chipping debris that must have been generated during the manufacture of these blades has been found at a late Halaf site.” (Campbell 1992: 184-185).</p>
<p>Arpachiyah Burnt House - Level TT6 — last Halaf level at Arpachiyah. Extremely rich finds found there. Polychrome pottery perhaps not as common as often believed. Also stone bowls — one of obsidian in the burnt house. Also obsidian links. Also seals and seal impressions. All of this material suggests that Arpachiyah exhibited control over others in the region in a formalized and direct manner. The large amounts of obsidian at Arpachiyah suggest a central role in exchange, and heightened ability to acquire needed resources. Davidson and McKerrall 1980 showed that 30-40% of pottery from Tepe Gawra originated from Arpachiyah using NAA. The Burnt House was probably last of a series of earlier iterations of similar design, suggesting that this control was not short-lived. The eponymous Burnt House is Later Halaf. Despite all this, the small size of Tell Arpachiyah and the variability of Halaf motifs suggest that control was rather limited to a small area. However central position in a trade network, or perhaps a social network, may have bolstered richness despite the small area covered.</p>
<p>Some larger Halaf sites are hinted but not excavated as of 1992 — Nineveh may have a Halaf layer, and Takyan Hoyuk is 12 hectares (Algaze et al 1991). What will this paper be about? I will draw attention to the distinction of north-eastern Mesopotamia during the Halaf period as shown through my network analysis and through other evaluations conducted by Campbell, Healey, etc. How will my paper distinguish itself? How can this be publishable as original research? I think I will have to orient this paper in a more theoretical light. This suits the motivations of this course. What aspects of the course can I touch upon? Building history up, rather than looking back upon it. How places are used as identifiers of power — the Burnt House as a place of social significance rather than Arpachiyah as deriving power from its spatial location. The resistance of and nullification of power — Week 7: Power, Political Landscapes, and Monumental Spaces (Dahomey as an analogy). Draw attention to the lack of truly phenomenological or sensory approaches.</p>
<p>Is the story of the Burnt House an event or reflective of longer term activities and behaviours? It seems that Campbell has trouble deciding, since he discusses the physical acts of individual agents as representative of longer-term norms. If burning down the house was not an act of everyday life (is this an acceptable and reasonable “if” to presume?) then how can it be reflective of typical life? It seems to be treated as a threshold, or a reaction to previous actions; as such, trying to figure out the state of living in pre-burning Arpachiyah is impossible by evaluating this non-typical event. I think if emphasis were placed on household or domestic features, a more purposeful evaluation can be made. In Campbell 1992, he starts off with a rather phenomenological approach but then gets bogged down by the luxury and elite goods and the broad-scale regional comparisons. At this point we know of the significance of Arpachiyah, and that there were regional centres. I generally agree with Kristiansen’s view that there was a shift to less decentralized and more hierarchical modes of regional organization, but can we say anything more than that? How does my network for Period 4 address this? There is clearly a distinction of NE Mesopotamia with an influx of new obsidian raw materials, and these are primarily arriving as worked products. I could analyze a new network consisting of sites within the “zone of Halaf influence” — Zagros Mountains to Euphrates and slightly beyond. I could filter the ties differently, at intervals of 5% similarity and graph density, number of modules, etc for each iteration, as well as mini-max (maximum threshold for minimum connectivity of the entire network). Maybe c-finder would be useful for highlighting overlap of influence that may have prompted conflict. Sites with varied assemblages, which do not fit into a particular GN module or have high betweenness centrality, may be considered to have been less dependent on a particular resource provider (consumer wins with increased competition) and may exhibit more market-oriented economic behaviour. On the other hand, those that are tighter-knit within a cluster are more dependent on a particular supplier and are likely engaged in chief-chief relationships whereby a power struggle is always present and decided upon by a few elite individuals who represent the larger group through their dealings with other leaders.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-12-11-notes-on-the-role-of-arpachiyah-and-the-socio-economic-landscape-of-the-halaf.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Space, Place and Landscape - Blog #4</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-10-17-space-place-and-landscape-blog-4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>I found this&nbsp;article written by Andrew Bevan of University College London&nbsp;really interesting and most relevant to my own interests. It is much more methodological in nature, and deals with issues that I hope to tackle throughout my doctoral studies. While I did take notes on some of the more minute methodological details, I’ll try to limit my comments here to broader issues that are more relevant to the course content.</p>
<p>This paper seems very processual in nature, however I don’t mean that in a negative way as is sometimes&nbsp;implied in some of our discussions. Bevan does invoke concepts from general/complex systems theory to document the settlement patterns on Kythera, however he does refrain from explicitly making&nbsp;certain conclusions in statistically-oriented language. For instance, in the section dealing with the development of intra-island hierarchies and site distributions, Bevan evaluated the potential relationships betweens the sizes of sites, the distances between them, and the concentrations of scatters, and his plots were interpreted&nbsp;in order to detect a potential hierarchy. He also noted the dynamic social, economic and political processes that would have led to such systems. Although Bevan never said so explicitly, his results are&nbsp;reminiscent of&nbsp;models depicting preferential attachment, which are observed in numerous natural and social settings, and which result in power law (also referred to as scale-free) statistical distributions. While this is not the setting to go into <a href="https://www.scottbot.net/HIAL/?p=17824">this specific phenomena and its implications</a>, I bring this up since&nbsp;such models&nbsp;are often criticized by social scientists because they tend to dehumanize the phenomena that underlie the material (transformed into&nbsp;data) being analyzed. Bevan sidestepped this issue by writing&nbsp;in archaeological terms, however the implication that humans simply react and impose reactions may still be troubling to some.</p>
<p>Similarly, in other sections, Bevan relies on models that restrict areas of human habitation to settings that support the “lowest common denominator” of comfort and survival. Although it was never made explicit, Bevan seems to follow a form of Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, which prioritizes physiological requirements and safety concerns over social considerations as primary movers of human activity.</p>
<p>While I doubt Bevan would adopt&nbsp;Maslow’s exact scheme, I’m of the opinion that humans are social in nature in accordance with the social brain theory <span class="citation" data-cites="dunbar1998">(Dunbar 1998)</span> and would give more credence to human interactions&nbsp;alongside largely independent needs. In&nbsp;light of the issues discussed in this course, these concerns&nbsp;relate to the role of individuals in society, and questions the degree to which we frame agency as&nbsp;imposed by&nbsp;social pressures, environmental variables, or personal motivations.</p>
<p>In any case, it is difficult to argue with the results that Bevan obtained. His evaluations do result in nice correlations that are discussed in light of anthropological and archaeological concerns, and he breaks down the assumptions that he makes in a responsible way. One could nit-pick on certain aspects of his methodology and data collections procedures, but with the exception of certain larger issues (using Kastri as an arbitrary reference point, for instance) this article seems well done in light of broader theoretical concerns. As mentioned earlier, Bevan avoids&nbsp;much criticism by not going too far with statistical analysis, but the&nbsp;underlying&nbsp;issues of humanistic considerations are still there and will be debated. My own stance is that&nbsp;we are animals and may be&nbsp;evaluated as such, but&nbsp;this does not have to be a restricting factor. For instance, as I mentioned in a previous comment regarding simulation of human activities and interactions, it may be considered more beneficial to use such methods to uncover the roles of certain processes through&nbsp;playing around with and tweaking various parameters (by&nbsp;<em>making</em> a game), rather than evaluating&nbsp;the final results or searching for <em>the</em> formula (<em>playing</em> or <em>experiencing</em>&nbsp;the game). All in all, I do see the usefulness of systems-based and computationally-modeled approaches, however they must be considered&nbsp;within anthropological and archaeological frameworks.</p>
<section id="commens" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="commens">Commens</h4>
<p><strong>Alex:</strong> I really enjoyed this post Zack and it definitely helped me to better understand Bevan’s article. I had difficulties with this week’s readings, no doubt because of my lack of experience with GIS or any computational models to study archaeological sites. But I can’t deny that the conclusions reached in each of the articles, and specifically Bevan’s, were both sound and convincing.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, like you mentioned, I was wary of Bevan’s method because I felt that his reduction of the traces of fundamentally human experience into data had a tendency to “dehumanize the phenomena.” It struck me that due to Bevan’s use of GIS, he was only able to speculate (with strong, circumstantial evidence of course) certain anthropological conclusions concerning cultural activity on Kythera.</p>
<p>I don’t think this necessarily weakens Bevan’s argument though, as his focus was not on uncovering lived social experience but determining “the way the landscape was structured.” In this way, I would be intrigued to see how the use of GIS or other computational models could support or engage with more post-processual theories we’ve looked at (it seems to me <span class="citation" data-cites="kosiba2013">Kosiba and Bauer (2013)</span> may have done this more effectively).</p>
<p><strong>Sean:</strong> To use Kosiba and Bauer’s terms, I think Bevan employs more of an interpretative application of GIS, rather than an econometric stance of human adaptation to climatic and geographic conditions. In my opinion, he does a good job of introducing the human voice (or at least some of the “decisions and dispositions” responsible for shaping a constructed landscape) into an otherwise robotic practice of computer modelling that sometimes makes rash assumptions about human nature. I especially enjoyed his section 3.1 on point pattern analysis, where he uses a randomized set of points in an attempt to flush out some of the human agency in site selection. The random points are plotted against actual site locations to identify patterns in distances between sites. As it turns out, there were significantly more actual sites located between 300 and 400 m apart than for the random points, which were averaged from 1000 simulation sets. The authors determined that this represented a deliberate spacing of contemporary sites, attributed to some combination of human motivating factors that for now can only be hypothesized.</p>
<p>While Bevan made a respectable, and largely successful, “interpretative leap from surface remains to actual settlement systems and their implications in testable, quantifiable ways” (2002:254), I think he still fell short in fully appreciating human interactions with their environment. In following Kosiba and Bauer’s conclusions about the interpretative system in GIS, the people in Bevan’s account “are lost within accounts that describe landscapes only in abstract, reductive terms of sites and regions” (2012:66). It seems that in the end, Bevan’s results concentrated primarily on numbers (i.e.&nbsp;population estimates) and frequency/distribution of rural sites. Perhaps he was not able to speculate more on the human decisions and activities involved because of the relative historic under appreciation or rural sites in the archaeological record. Perhaps this GIS approach was a crucial first step towards a more inclusive interpretation that consists of the political landscape, made up of all the “social categories and spatial boundaries that influence and guide how people perceive their surroundings” <span class="citation" data-cites="kosiba2013">(Kosiba and Bauer 2013: 67)</span>.</p>
<p>In the end, Alex I think you’re correct in thinking that Bevan’s argument is not weakened by his ultimate reliance on speculative conclusions about the cultural forces responsible for the observed patterns. Like you said, his focus was to determine how the landscape was structured, not to uncover the social and political institutional foundations for the organization of Neopalatial rural Kytheran landscapes. I do think that is the next step in expanding this field of research, however, and am also interested to find out how others might engage with the current theoretical playing field.</p>
<p><strong>Zack:</strong> Sean, I definitely agree with your notion that this study is one step in a larger and more inclusive interpretation of the social and political landscape, and realistically a totally holistic approach would not be possible without drawing from various perspectives. And I also appreciate Alex pointing out Bevan’s stated purpose, which I had not seriously considered in my post. This article seems like it would fit well within an edited volume containing different views on the landscape of Kythera.</p>
<p>I’m left wondering whether it is necessary to adopt more phenomenological issues in GIS studies, or whether it is acceptable to take on a more systematic perspective on its own. In general I don’t see much overlap between these perspectives in the archaeology of island interactions, perhaps because the boundaries and limitations imposed by such geographies make it tempting to conduct similar systematic investigations (see <span class="citation" data-cites="knappett2008a">Knappett, Evans, and Rivers (2008)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="broodbank2000">Broodbank (2000)</span> for examples of this). I think that viewshed analysis and other mappings relating to human senses is a potential way of more effectively linking the phenomenological and systematic perspectives, however as noted in the comments on Daiana’s blog, such an opportunity was not fully taken advantage of by <span class="citation" data-cites="willians2006">(<strong>willians2006?</strong>)</span></p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-broodbank2000" class="csl-entry">
Broodbank, C. 2000. <em>An <span>Island Archaeology</span> of the <span>Early Cyclades</span></em>. Cambridge University Press. <a href="http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/156376/">http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/156376/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dunbar1998" class="csl-entry">
Dunbar, Robin I. M. 1998. <span>“The Social Brain Hypothesis.”</span> <em>Evolutionary Anthropology: Issues, News, and Reviews</em> 6 (5): 178–90. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1520-6505(1998)6:5<178::AID-EVAN5>3.0.CO;2-8">https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1520-6505(1998)6:5&lt;178::AID-EVAN5&gt;3.0.CO;2-8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-knappett2008a" class="csl-entry">
Knappett, Carl, Tim Evans, and Ray Rivers. 2008. <span>“Modelling Maritime Interaction in the <span>Aegean Bronze Age</span>.”</span> <em>Antiquity</em> 82 (318): 1009–24. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003598X0009774X">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003598X0009774X</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-kosiba2013" class="csl-entry">
Kosiba, Steve, and Andrew M. Bauer. 2013. <span>“Mapping the Political Landscape: Toward a <span>GIS</span> Analysis of Environmental and Social Difference.”</span> <em>Journal of Archaeological Method and Theory</em> 20 (1): 61–101. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10816-011-9126-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10816-011-9126-z</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-10-17-space-place-and-landscape-blog-4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Communicating social theory</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-10-06-communicating-social-theory.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>While discussing Tim Ingold’s work in class today, and going over the ways that he conveys his ideas, I began to think about how we construct and communicate an understanding of the world around us as social scientists. The use of analogy is really interesting because comparative examples get points across very effectively. Also, there is a tendency for social theories to be commonly structured in terms of dialectical relationships or dualities, which suggest an opposition between two forces, a common structure in myth-making. I’m left wondering whether similar comparisons between social theory and mythology can be made.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I recently re-watched one of my favourite episodes of Star Trek for the gazillionth time, <em>Darmok</em>. In this episode, the Enterprise encounters representatives of the Children of Tama, or the Tamarians, a society that has puzzled the federation for generations due to their seemingly incomprehensible language. Their language primarily consists of many proper nouns and grand actions, however without understanding the meaning behind these names and the situations behind the actions mentioned, it is impossible to fully comprehend what is being communicated. As is implied throughout the episode, these recurrent words refer to scenes from mythology, and the Tamarians communicate via analogy to these commonly understood ideas.</p>
<p>It was only through re-creation of elements in these stories that Picard was able to understand anything that Dathon, the Tamarian captain, was trying to communicate. They beam down to an isolated planet, where Dathon hands Picard a knife. Picard totally misunderstood this gesture as an invitation to duel, but later on he opened his mind a bit when he began to notice various other gestures contradicting this assumption. Moreover, Picard realizes that there is hope to understand the language, and that understanding it may in fact lead to positive outcomes. When Picard realized that they were in danger, that there was a problem that could be resolved through Dathon’s proposed gesture, he was totally willing to play along in order to overcome the conflict. Dathon was critically wounded in the fight, and as he lay dying, Picard had his amazing a-ha! moment when everything seemed to click, in a similar way as when a puzzling concept gets untangled in my own mind. Finally, through his retelling of the Epic of Gilgamesh to Dathon, Picard develops a more complete understanding of how to communicate with him and the rest of the Tamarian people. Through this, Picard realizes that his own life, and his already established way of doing things, were already influenced by the same ideas that make up the Tamarian language.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-10-06-communicating-social-theory.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Space, Place and Landscape - Blog #3</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-26-space-place-and-landscape-blog-3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>In the book chapter&nbsp;I read this week - Yi-Fu Tuan’s <em>Space, Time, Place: A Humanistic Frame</em> — the author outlines how space, time and place&nbsp;are commonly conceptualized from a humanistic (= anthropological?) perspective. He&nbsp;examines the nature of these these elements (for lack of a better term) at&nbsp;four scales (I’m unsure if “scale” is used in the same way we refer to it). This chapter&nbsp;is divided into sub-sections encompassing discussion pertaining to each of these scales, which are labeled as follows:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>time in mythic space;</li>
<li>Greek-Hebrew models of space, time and place;</li>
<li>time and experiential space; and</li>
<li>time and place.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Time in mythic space:</strong> Tuan observes that mythic space occurs in three ways: cosmogonic, astronomic, and human. The first kind refers to origin myths, the second to observations of natural phenomena, and the third to human experiences. While the author notes&nbsp;that cosmogonic and human space tend to be expressed in terms of linear development (a progression from beginning to end), astronomic space is more rhythmic or cyclical in nature. Tuan&nbsp;then outlines various conceptualizations of mythic space through ethnographic examples in order to illustrate&nbsp;how these conceptions are actually put into practice.</p>
<p><strong>Space, time, place: Greek-Hebrew models:</strong> Tuan then goes over two case studies wherein he&nbsp;outlines supposed conceptualizations of space pertaining to Greek and Hebrew societies. However I found this section extremely problematic in a couple&nbsp;ways. First, the author&nbsp;did not draw upon enough&nbsp;primary sources derived from classical texts and archaeological evidence in order to derive his&nbsp;arguments in a convincing way (at least to me, a former classics student). Am I to assume that Tuan’s reference to&nbsp;Pericles’ speeches, without pointing to specific notions that this Athenian politician&nbsp;may have presented, are representative of&nbsp;Athenian — let alone pan-Hellenic — attitudes? Tuan also generalizes&nbsp;the group of people he&nbsp;refers to as Hebrews, who probably had very distinctive conceptualizations of space, time and place at different points in time (pre- and post-diaspora, for instance). However as I read this while sitting with family who came together from many places to celebrate&nbsp;the Jewish new year, I do recognize some truth in Tuan’s representation of Jewish (or Hebrew) tendencies to “build in time” and “temporalize” the structures they build (p.&nbsp;10). But&nbsp;this should not be compartmentalized as a Jewish phenomenon, and may also potentially be observed in other groups&nbsp;exhibiting&nbsp;similar histories and community structures.</p>
<p>I also believe that Tuan used this section to construct a notion of “western” conceptions of space, time and place. I only bring this up because we discussed this in earlier blog comments and in class, and I don’t want to open that can of worms again, but&nbsp;the idea that early Medieval models of the universe were derived as a synthesis of Greek and Hebrew conceptualizations seems overly simplistic to me. Although additional arguments against this notion can likely be made, it is easiest to point out the&nbsp;considerable temporal gaps between Classical Greece (5th century BCE), 1st century AD Judaism/Christianity, and the Early Middle&nbsp;Ages (c.&nbsp;400 - 1000 AD).</p>
<p><strong>Time and experiential space:</strong> This section describes&nbsp;how space is used to convey notions of time, and vice versa. Tuan prompts discussion&nbsp;by referencing many common colloquial phrases, and the implied&nbsp;meanings behind them, that refer to time in spatial terms. However I find that some of Tuan’s interpretations&nbsp;crossover with&nbsp;ideas he&nbsp;presents in his&nbsp;first section dealing with&nbsp;mythic representations of space. Now perhaps I’m confusing apples and oranges here, but I felt that the author’s example of his&nbsp;drive to and from work at dawn and dusk complicates the notion he&nbsp;presents earlier that&nbsp;human space is&nbsp;conceptualized in linear terms. A purely linear perspective of time&nbsp;supports an intentional aspect to agency, with each person reading their own path — however the social structure in which we live brings habit into our lives, such as the cycle of driving to and from work at specific points in the day. Although Tuan only wrote this book chapter around a year after Giddens’ canonical work was published, I do think that&nbsp;perspectives of time play into ideas of agency and structure and should be explored more thoroughly in this light. I also think that this must tie in to the different wavelengths of history presented by Braudel and other members of the Annales School, but&nbsp;to be honest I am not entirely sure how they explicitly relate. Perhaps this will be discussed in more detail next class, and the relationship between structuration theory and the annales school will be made more clear.</p>
<p>Moreover, in this section Tuan explains how contemplation influences our perceptions of distance and extent of time. After reading his&nbsp;quote,&nbsp;“Objects, space and time also become visible — no longer the mere coordinates for habitual behaviours — when they are contemplated” (p.&nbsp;12-13), I am unsure about whether this refers to empirical measurement or critical thought. From the tone of the article the latter is implied, however for some reason this brings to mind Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle (which dictates that an object or entity whose properties are&nbsp;measured is altered through the act of&nbsp;physical observation, and is thus not in its natural or pristine state that it takes when unobserved), which is more concerned with the observation of physical things. Are&nbsp;the conceptual and physical dictated by the same laws or guidelines? Perhaps this question would be better&nbsp;addressed to humanists&nbsp;or philosophers.</p>
<p><strong>Time and place:</strong> I find that this section was more cryptic than the rest. There were some short phrases that seemed out out place or without context, assuming that the reader would be able to&nbsp;come up with the implied meaning. I do think that Tuan’s&nbsp;idea of place as a static state is problematic. If I&nbsp;remember a&nbsp;family trip to Maine one summer, and recall the places where I was (the town where I was staying, the house we rented, the beach, the car ride there and back, etc), I will not remember them in static ways. Instead I will remember the experiences&nbsp;I had with my family, which were dynamic and occurred over the course of a few weeks. The multiplicity of times and places, which transcend scales, are far from being&nbsp;“one relation between time and space” (Tuan’s definition of place, p.&nbsp;14). Although I could not really understand the main point Tuan was trying to make in this section, I do disagree with this fundamental notion that he&nbsp;brings up.</p>
<p><strong>Overall synthesis:</strong> This was an interesting and fun read, however I think that it was too brief for the broad scope of ideas covered. Although I have not yet read his other work, Yi-Fu Tuan, who is credited by many as the founder of human geography, has written extensively on the relationship between space, time and place, so&nbsp;perhaps the criticism I made&nbsp;is not warranted in the larger scope of his work. However I think that this particular book chapter would have been more informative&nbsp;if&nbsp;these sections were broken up into their own dedicated works, with more elaborate discussion dedicated to the ideas presented by others&nbsp;whom Tuan&nbsp;references.</p>
<section id="comments" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments">Comments</h4>
<p><strong>Alex:</strong> I felt the same way as you Zack when I was reading this chapter. I was underwhelmed by what I thought was a lack of sources or groundwork in Tuan’s essay. Specifically, in the section “Time and Experiential Space” I was intrigued by how Tuan considered the effect contemplation has on our experience of distance and time. This is a point I hope to bring up in class with regards to Heidegger, as I think his argument is much stronger whereas Tuan seemed to lack the “philosophical rigour” I have come to expect in such discussions. The essay did feel almost like an introduction to a book, which makes me wonder like you whether our criticisms would be answered further in the project.</p>
<p><strong>Mary:</strong> Zack I liked your critique of Tuan’s generalization of his Greek and Hebrew societies. I felt that his examples were over simplified versions of reality but they did fit neatly into his narrative and nicely illustrated the difficult concepts he was explaining.</p>
<p>Maybe Alex is right and this chapter didn’t insight the ‘philosophical rigor’ that is usually associated with these kinds of discussions but I felt that it was written to allow an entry point for people to start understanding time and space in a new way. People, like me, who feel they are playing catch-up with experience in such theoretical and philosophical conversations, will greatly appreciate Tuan’s approach.</p>
<p><strong>Sean:</strong> Zack, in response to your “humanistic = anthropological” question mark at the beginning. I think that at this point (in 1978) usage of the term “humanistic” in the field of geography was largely equated with an approach that considers “human agency” as central to their study; or in other words, they considered the value and/or visibility of the “decisions and dispositions” of humans in the archaeological record. I could be wrong, but when Tuan says “humanism” I think he just means that he is thinking in terms of how humans conceptualize and interact with the “space, time and place” that surrounds them, which I think is pretty respectable considering it was written almost four decades ago.</p>
<p>In terms of the article, I actually quite enjoyed it. Overall, I would have to agree with Mary here. It might not have been couched in the philosophical traditions that would now be required of such an investigation of these principles, but it does allow for an effective method of understanding and appreciating these issues.</p>
<p>You are certainly right to question the author’s temporal variability in his choice of case studies, but I don’t think the discrepancies are problematic in this situation. If he was using these as comparative examples in any attempt to prove their relation to each other, it probably would have been a bad move. But I think he used them as examples to illuminate how many ways human perspectives have manifested themselves in the minds and societies that have existed over time.</p>
<p>At the end, Tuan accuses the field of human geography of largely ignoring “time as a dimension of human experience” (16). Ultimately, he is proposing that the field of geography begin really considering these experiences of humanity in order to infuse a sense of reality into the geographer’s world. In this way, it is not meant as a philosophical or even anthropological piece (in terms of who the primary audience was expected to be), so we might be able to forgive him for not being so thorough in his philosophical underpinnings.</p>
<p>And finally, as Alex mentioned, this article is situated at the very beginning of a good sized book entitled “Making Sense of Time”, so perhaps this chapter was not intended to entirely justify the humanistic approach, but merely to approach these topics and set the stage for further discussion later on. I, for one, don’t really feel like reading the rest of the book just to find out though…</p>
<p><strong>Zack:</strong> Okay, it seems that I’ve been a bit too not-picky here, and after re-reading it I do see this as a useful introductory piece that gets us into the idea of what phenemenology can be about. It seems like an odd fit in relation to other readings in the syllabus, but figuring out the intended audience really clarified its value to me.</p>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Hey Zack, thanks for the overview — we will definitely dig into this some more tomorrow. I wonder if you or anybody else can you perhaps see what Tuan is bringing to the table that the other phenomenology we read this week aren’t? BTW, Sean is basically right on this — although more specifically the use of “humanist” is referring specifically to how geographers studied space previously, which was empirically-rich but fairly abstract and certainly not focused on the “experienced”.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-26-space-place-and-landscape-blog-3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Space, Place and Landscape - Blog #2</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-21-space-place-and-landscape-blog-2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>This week I was assigned to blog about the article written by Joyce,&nbsp;<em>Unintended Consequences? Monumentality as a Novel Experience in Formative Mesoamerica</em>,&nbsp;which reevaluates the circumstances that may have led to the construction of monuments during the Formative Period in Mesoamerica. Joyce illustrates how the first clay platforms were constructed using knowledge from prior experience working&nbsp;with the same materials, and speculates on how they were perceived by those who lived alongside them when they were first built. She dismisses the idea that monuments were built for their own sake, and instead proposes that the notable platforms were the result of normal practices used when&nbsp;constructing houses&nbsp;upon the site of a preceding structure. The larger surface area in which the clay was laid out&nbsp;resulted in extended longevity for the structure and social differentiation for people associated with it via phenomenological&nbsp;control and access restrictions.</p>
<p>Joyce draws on the work of <span class="citation" data-cites="giddens1977">(<strong>giddens1977?</strong>)</span> in order to highlight the role of&nbsp;already existing structure&nbsp;and practices&nbsp;in shaping new socio-political developments. The author guides us through a scenario in which an actor would initiate the construction of a grand monument in an explicitly&nbsp;intentional manner, which is shown to be not that realistic. Instead, Joyce proposes that the permanence of these platforms results from similar practices as before, albeit&nbsp;performed under different circumstances, namely the application of clay onto a wider and flatter surface. This means that the mobilization of labour would have likely&nbsp;occurred within the already-existing social structure featuring already-existing practices.</p>
<p>However what if the social structure of the status quo (prior to “monumental” platforms) was already of a manner that would have favoured socio-political control or the restriction of specialized knowledge? Although the readings this week emphasized the relationships between place and power, at times I felt that place was given too much attention as a way of solidifying control. Monuments and control of special places are useful in that regard, however what about the role of clothing, jewelry, or other alienable or inalienable possessions? And what about&nbsp;restricted knowledge or practices? If some form of social influence was already in effect then the unlikely&nbsp;scenario posed by Joyce, in which an actor somehow convinces her community to drop everything and build a monument, may contain some credibility after all. However a solid rebuttal to this counter-argument is that these things may all be associated with certain places (i.e.&nbsp;raw materials come from a certain place; knowledge is often inspired&nbsp;by nature, which occurs at a place), and that social differentiation is derived from control over the thing’s use, which may be best accomplished through control of the places from which the things may be derived. So it seems that I’ve come full circle (… I think) and ultimately I’m a bit confused after writing out this post. Maybe after thinking about this some more, and reading some of the comments, I’ll update with further thoughts.</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> Following Dr.&nbsp;Roddick’s prompts, I re-read Joyce’s article with more attention paid to the high theory involved. The author clearly draws from Giddens’ duality of structure and agency, a theoretical pillar that recognizes the roles of individual agents in the reproduction and transformation of social structure that in turn feedbacks into the actions of individuals. At the core of Giddens’ work is his&nbsp;appreciation of the role of individual human agents in shaping social structure through persistence or repetition of certain cultural practices, rather than&nbsp;characterizing&nbsp;societies&nbsp;based on the institutions in place. Giddens&nbsp;draws an analogy to&nbsp;languages to explain his&nbsp;ideas in a more relatable way; language is simply and effectively the encryption and decryption of information by parties with a mutual understanding of the meanings behind words and letters, and the “rules” for processing information are rather implicit to those communicating. As with social structure, the rules of transferring information or ways of acting are implicit in&nbsp;our minds, however they are loosely defined based on the behaviour of others in the collective. As people tend to view the world differently and interact in different ways, languages and social protocol shift as well. The actions of and interactions between individuals thus shape the overall social structure, yet actors are concurrently influenced by this worldview that they shape. The implicit nature of protocols that shape social structure&nbsp;suggests a degree of un-inentionality in the actions of agents, an issue that came up&nbsp;when characterizing&nbsp;agency in class, albeit briefly in preparation for a more in-depth discussion later on.</p>
<p>Joyce tied in structuration theory after recognizing that the construction of later monumental platforms could have been derived from practices already in place prior to the explicit intention of building monuments. The&nbsp;phenomenological changes that arose from the construction of certain larger platforms would have occurred unintentionally, rather than as a result of intentional motivations to build a monument. While I don’t claim to have any &nbsp;knowledge regarding phenomenology, I think that the cognitive changes that drove these societal shifts need to be made more explicit, and that discussion on transformation itself remains the weakest link in Joyce’s argument. Although the author does refer to Love’s work&nbsp;(published a 1999 volume co-edited by&nbsp;Joyce), I have not had the chance to read this&nbsp;yet.</p>
<p>Joyce recognizes that social structure is a product of individuals’ actions, and that peoples’ actions — which are often unintentionally driven — are the result of social pressures. At the surface this seems kind of cyclical, but it does seem to make sense. I just feel that we need to be able to map the processes involved in these transformations better, and perhaps formalize&nbsp;the way that Giddens’ structuration theory is applied.</p>
<p><strong>About Rosemary Joyce:</strong> Rosemary Joyce is&nbsp;an anthropological archaeologist at UC Berkeley, and is a leading figure in the field of social archaeology. Her work&nbsp;focuses on&nbsp;ceramic analysis, household archaeology, and the archaeology of sex and gender,&nbsp;but these interests seem to stem out into other related fields as well. Joyce has a blog, <a href="https://ancientbodies.wordpress.com/">Ancient Bodies, Ancient Lives</a>, where she reflects on perceptions of sex and gender of the past as portrayed in contemporary media and archaeology news reports, providing a more&nbsp;informed&nbsp;perspective for the general public in amazingly accessible language and format.</p>
<section id="comments" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments">Comments</h4>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Hi Zack, Maybe I can make a suggestion here? Perhaps you (and with the help of others) can dig into the key “big question” of the article, the high theory if you will, which revolves around the idea of structuration vis-a-vis bigger debates around structure: agency. Perhaps give us a bit more on structuration. Of course we briefly introduced the notion of agency last week. Perhaps we can work towards the nitty gritty of Gidden’s idea, and how Joyce is using this to help understand agency and structure in the context of early sites in Mesoamerica. What is Joyce’s view on those troubling issues of “intention” and agency as individuals, which we also discussed last week in our introduction to agency. Then turn to think through the how this is explored in the archaeological data. In other words, go from the “high theory” to the nuts and bolts of the case study.</p>
<p><strong>Alex:</strong> After reading your update, I felt like I had a better grasp of the way Joyce links the theoretical idea of structuration and agency to the example of monumentality in Formative Mesoamerica. Specifically, I liked your comment that “the cognitive changes that drove these societal shifts need to be made more explicit, and that discussion on transformation itself remains the weakest link in Joyce’s argument.” Though I understand your point that such a link presents a weakness in Joyce’s argument, I think we could give her more credit. Taken as a hypothetical, Joyce’s claim that early “monumental” platforms caused a phenomenological shift through unintended consequences can be useful to us as a mode of investigation.</p>
<p>Let me try to be a little more clear. I think that the strongest aspect of Joyce’s essay was her refusal to accept explanations for early monumental platforms based in our contemporary perception of monumentality today. Instead, by focusing on the unintended consequences of building these platforms, she forces us to rethink the beginnings of monumentality outside of a presentist view. I find such an investigative strategy intellectually courageous and admirable. And despite the empirical strength of her claim, I feel her strategy alone is significant.</p>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Very nicely put. Another way to say it, is that Joyce is concerned with “looking up” through time, rather than looking back. Many explanations for transformations are based heavily upon what emerged. In contrast, Joyce is interested in thinking through the materials, and previous experiences with those materials (in this case, clay), and the potential ripple effect they may have had. For instance, “new concept of architecture as something potentially more permanent may have shifted the way that residential structures were assessed, placing a greater value on permanency in those as well. At Puerto Escondido, for example, the use of lime plaster and stone facings becomes a feature of monumental earthen and of residential architecture simultaneously, with the earliest plastered platforms platforms dating to 1100-900 B.C. Prior to that point, our construction evidence suggests buildings with post frameworks supported perishable superstructures, and these buildings were remodeled many times in succession.” (p.&nbsp;19). We can actually think of architecture that’s still with us today in a similar fashion. For instance, does anyone know the story behind front porches in North America?</p>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> …and thanks Zack for the update — we’ll definitely explore this in more detail tomorrow!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-21-space-place-and-landscape-blog-2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Re-evaluating Heterarchy and Peer-Polity Interaction</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-16-reevaluating-heterarchy-and-peer-polity-interaction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>One of the major criticisms made by my thesis committee was on my suggestion that&nbsp;peer-polity interaction be more readily adopted as a framework to base future network analysis studies upon. Although now I am beginning to realize my error, I think that this stems from my misunderstanding of what peer-polity interaction really was meant to address — the scaling up of polities into “fully fledged” city states (although I must read more to verify this and gain a more complete understanding — Renfrew,&nbsp;Ma, Schortman, Snodgrass, etc). The value that I saw (and still see) with peer-polity interaction is regarding the focus on relationships among unranked entities on the same plane, which have the potential to be ranked given the unevenness of relationships among them. This notion is probably better evoked by&nbsp;heterarchy, as defined by Crumley (and by Schortman who raises similar points more explicitly regarding PPI as well). But is peer-polity interaction an instance of heterarchical thought? It does emphasize the tenets of heterarchy, but perhaps with a certain more focused aim in mind. However I must find out what this aim truly is through more focused reading of the aforementioned&nbsp;sources, among others. Schortman seems to be key for understanding the relationship between heterarchy and PPI.</p>
<p>So I think that I can adequately re-focus&nbsp;chapter 2 (or was it 3?), which currently attempts to highlight comparative approaches and ppi specifically, to discussion more focused on heterarchy more broadly. Specifically, its potential use&nbsp;for&nbsp;the analysis of distributed systems is quite pertinent.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-16-reevaluating-heterarchy-and-peer-polity-interaction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Space, Place and Landscape - Blog #1</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-13-space-place-and-landscape-blog1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>This week I read William Balée’s 2006 article <em>The Research Program of Historical Ecology</em> along with some other writings on more ecologically-driven approaches to anthropological notions of space, place and landscape. Balée starts off by outlining the main postulates of historical ecology, which he considers to be a set of ideas adopted by&nbsp;certain likeminded scholars that frame discussion along similar lines of thought. The author summarizes these tenets as follows:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol type="a">
<li>Practically all environments on Earth have been affected by humans, including in a broad sense behavioural activities of the genus <em>Homo</em>, although others would limit the wide-ranging effect of humans on the environment to only the entire time dating&nbsp;from the beginning of the Holocene, that is, the time coinciding with the beginning of agriculture;</li>
<li>human nature is not programmed genetically or otherwise to lessen or augment species diversity and other environmental parameters;</li>
<li>it follows that kinds of societies defined by various socioeconomic, political and cultural criteria impact landscapes in dissimilar ways … and</li>
<li>human interactions with landscapes in a broad variety of historical and ecological contexts may be studied as a total (integrative) phenomenon</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Historical ecology is framed by Balée as being&nbsp;empirical yet guided by social theoretic perspectives that tend to be primarily situated on the middle to low theory range. He compares the research program of primary interest with other ways of thinking about human-environment interaction, and&nbsp;after wading through some of the more pedantic differentiation or commonalities posed by the author, I do&nbsp;actually recognize some&nbsp;diversity. Following Dr.&nbsp;Roddick’s suggestion, I tried to think about the disciplinary divisions as a landscape of sorts, and I even sketched out a mind-map on a napkin.</p>
<p>Although I won’t summarize all of that chicken scratch right now, it is clear that historical ecology takes on more of the middle and low ranges of theory, in that the effects of certain&nbsp;actions are thoroughly assessed, and that human social, economic and cultural organization is considered in a rather broad way that focuses on cultural processes akin to most other current anthropological perspectives adopted by archaeologists. However Balée does take for granted certain ideas that I feel should be re-evaluated. For instance, his notion&nbsp;that historical ecology arose out of the inadequacy of prior schools of thought to consider human-environment interaction in <em>complex societies</em>&nbsp;(p.&nbsp;76) presumes that a strict division exists between societies deemed either as complex or&nbsp;simple, at least in the minds of certain scholars. While historical ecology does seem to bridge this dichotomy by thinking of cultural process in a broader sense, a more thorough overview of what is meant by those terms as used in this review, and&nbsp;as they were used by those who the author is critical of, would have been nice to include.</p>
<p>Another concern I have is how <em>impact</em> is considered and defined. The scale of time or of actions (e.g.&nbsp;the interplay between the idea&nbsp;of one person ploughing a field or tending to crops vs.&nbsp;‘agriculture’ being defined as a socio-economic phenomenon) for a change wrought&nbsp;by humans to be considered long-term isn’t clearly defined, however it is implied that the triggering or disturbance of an agglomerating system by a human is of primary consideration. This confusion is understandable since individual&nbsp;actors and actions are often difficult to highlight&nbsp;in such a system that is said to represent ‘society’ and the impact of the collective (especially when looking back in time), but&nbsp;little acknowledgement of these challenges&nbsp;is given. I think that this is important when thinking about middle-range assessments because everything we observe in such a way&nbsp;is&nbsp;the result of many individual actions performed by people who possess their own agency alongside and separate&nbsp;from their neighbours or other members of the collective. I think that Balée dismisses the discipline of environmental history too harshly, and that its tendency to&nbsp;focus on&nbsp;evaluation of&nbsp;historical case studies may actually be useful for examining the potential impacts of certain kinds of actors to the development of a system.</p>
<p>This is a great overview of the disciplinary boundaries and theoretical variation that exist in a seemingly focused field of study, but in general it also reinforces an archetype of the position of anthropology among other neighbouring disciplines such as classics, environmental science and history. Classics tends to be more focused on minutia in particular societies as viewed from a socio-political perspective, (I think that classics has the potential to go way beyond the study of Classical Greece and Rome, and to develop its own middle-range perspectives, but I’ll&nbsp;hold off on this discussion for now). environmental science grounds the foundation of arguments in facts of nature from a scientific angle, and history allows us to think about the relationships between temporal scales, whereas anthropological archaeology deals with socio-economic and cultural dynamics on a very middle-range theoretical scale. In this article historical ecology, which is highly influenced by anthropological perspectives, is positioned as a unifying knot that can tie the&nbsp;other&nbsp;sub-disciplines&nbsp;mentioned together, (This brings to mind the quote by Alfred Kroeber, “Anthropology is the most humanistic of the sciences and the most scientific of the humanities.”) but anthropology may also be perceived of as having its very own focus that should be recognized more explicitly. Social theory is a great way to tease out these idiosyncrasies and enable&nbsp;the work done among these disciplines to be stitched together in a more complementary fashion.</p>
<section id="comments" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments">Comments</h4>
<p><strong>Andy:</strong> Hi Zack, That’s quite a mind map! (It would be interesting to see that digitally). You can imagine how this would represent one corner of our theoretical landscape, with some like Balée and Clark Erickson (anyone note that he was thanked at the end of this article?) spending considerable time, whereas others doing landscape studies may not visit at all. Which, of course, begs the question why/why not? I wonder if you can explain this a bit: “it is clear that historical ecology takes on more of the middle and low ranges of theory, in that the effects of certain actions are thoroughly assessed, and that human social, economic and cultural organization is considered in a rather broad way that focuses on cultural processes akin to most other current anthropological perspectives adopted by archaeologists.” A little later you suggest that anthropological archaeology deals primarily at the middle-range level (as opposed to history). Perhaps others have thoughts too?</p>
<p><strong>Zack:</strong> Maybe I’m using these terms wrong, but I was referring to the low/middle/high ranges of theory mentioned briefly in the last class. High theory was described as more lofty, low theory was referred to with regards to more direct interpretation of the material record, and middle was described as situated somewhere between the other two. I may have been generalizing when I stated my views on the focuses of different disciplines, but I do think that there are certain emphases on these ranges, guided by the questions that each tries to address and the evidence that tends to be considered.</p>
<p><strong>Sean:</strong> My understanding is that middle-range theory had its origins in things like ethnoarchaeology and experimental archaeology, which allow us to make certain assumptions (or interpretations) of behaviours or activities in the past based on current observations. It considers things like taphonomic processes and bioturbation, and other effects of time and environment on the archaeological record, to judge how cultural deposits are disturbed over long periods of time. Call me crazy, but that sounds awfully similar to what we have been reading about historical ecology. It takes input from various fields and observations in the present (i.e.&nbsp;geography, biology, agriculture, fishing, forestry, you name it) and applies them to the past, ultimately curious in the cumulative effects of human interaction with the environment (a.k.a. landscape). I think that because of this, and because it examines communities on a regional scale and therefore their interactions with other communities or cultures, historical ecology is primarily a middle and high range theory. It looks at long-term processes that are applicable cross-culturally and within complex landscapes.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-13-space-place-and-landscape-blog1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Space, Place and Landscape</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-09-space-place-and-landscape.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>This semester I’m taking a graduate course called The Anthropology of Space, Place and Landscape, which has a heavy emphasis on social theory. Hopefully this course will help me to ground myself within social theory vis-a-vis geo-spatial archaeology, and help me figure out how to better involve these ideas in my own work. I already have an idea to work with&nbsp;for the research paper, which will focus on a certain area covered in my M.A.&nbsp;thesis, and hopefully will also be publishable.</p>
<p>This is my second course taught by Dr.&nbsp;Roddick, and like with Writing the Field,&nbsp;it involves a blogging component. This is meant to prompt critical reflection on the readings and keep us on our toes between classes. My first piece will written this week, so stay tuned…</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-09-space-place-and-landscape.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Star Trek and Classics</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-01-star-trek-and-classics.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Star Trek may best be viewed from the eyes of classicists. Classics is normally associated with the study of Greek and Roman culture and civic society during their respective classical periods, and the particular focus on these areas of interest is deeply rooted in western European socio-political ideals and scholarship&nbsp;that emerged from&nbsp;the Renaissance to the late 19th century. While critics of the discipline point towards&nbsp;the extensive research that has been done on these particular geographical and temporal settings as detriments, I believe that classics is really about the study of specific&nbsp;kinds of societies from a particular angle that emphasizes attention towards the nature of&nbsp;civic society, relationships between foreign and domestic affairs, and the impact of myth and public memory on contemporary society. While many classicists today may not realize&nbsp;it, this definition certainly does not limit classical research to ancient Greece and Rome. These issues&nbsp;were faced by many societies throughout history, and persist today. These are themes that are even commonly dealt with in fiction!</p>
<p>As my first classics professor taught me, the discipline in called classics because it is the study of a society that is considered to be in a class of its own. Under this definition, classics may be broadened to include the study of&nbsp;notable societies for which detailed material and textual evidence is available, examined through a critical socio-political perspective.</p>
<p>[This post was never completed.]</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Star Trek</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-09-01-star-trek-and-classics.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Github for archaeological databases</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-08-03-github-for-archaeological-databases.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Today I&nbsp;submitted an abstract for a poster presentation at the AIA Annual Meeting in January on the <a href="http://zackbatist.github.io/DObsiSS/">Database of Obsidian Sourcing Studies (DObsiSS)</a>,&nbsp;a compilation of obsidian sourcing results pertaining to Neolithic contexts in southwest Asia and Anatolia. I made this database for my M.A.&nbsp;thesis, which utilizes network analysis in order to assess and re-conceptualize Neolithization and regional interaction in this setting. I recently made DObsiSS&nbsp;available on Github, so anyone can access&nbsp;the data or commit modifications.&nbsp;Although Github (and the git protocol at its core) is primarily a code-sharing platform, it’s seen some great&nbsp;applications in the realm of <a href="http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/tag/github101">academic writing</a>&nbsp;and <a href="http://blog.okfn.org/2013/07/02/git-and-github-for-data/">scientific database management</a>. A great introduction to git&nbsp;for scientists and academics is available <a href="http://nyuccl.org/pages/GitTutorial/">here</a>, and a more practical guide can be found <a href="http://rogerdudler.github.io/git-guide/">here</a>.</p>
<p>I think that there is a lot of potential&nbsp;for the use of git to manage&nbsp;archaeological databases. It enables&nbsp;data sharing and re-use, encourages&nbsp;collaboration and communication among members of the community, makes work more transparent, and breaks down the common notion that archaeological databases exist in isolation or can ever be “complete”. Interestingly, the&nbsp;antithesis to these concerns seem to be the thorniest issues in archaeological data management.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>The Database of Obsidian Sourcing Studies (DObsiSS): Using Git for Collaborative Management of Archaeological Data</strong><br>
The Database of Obsidian Sourcing Studies (DObsiSS) is an integrated listing of chemically characterized archaeological obsidian compiled from published journal articles, excavation reports, conference papers and other scholarly records. Obsidian is a volcanic glass that was used throughout prehistory to produce razor sharp cutting tools, and it has chemical properties that enable archaeologists to identify the source from which the raw material derives. This information is used to determine whether the inhabitants of a site participated in large-scale exchange networks, as well as the capacity of their involvement. Although a large amount of data has been generated over the years, obsidian sourcing studies tend to be done independently, with results published in journals aimed towards specialized researchers, detailed in regional-journal field reports, or kept as supplementary material in databases held by archaeometric laboratories. Aside from the issue of data accessibility, the redundancy of published results and a lack of standardization among laboratories complicate efforts to compare and analyze all of this information. The database presented here is the result of an effort to make this immense wealth of data more useful for archaeologists or for academics of other disciplines.</p>
<p>DObsiSS is an open access online resource that is continuously updated to include newly published data. The database operates using git –– a collaborative data sharing protocol that allows anyone to commit proposals for modification, submit new content to be added, and track any changes in a transparent manner. It is also a great platform for discussion, where anyone may enquire about particular proposed modifications or make suggestions for larger improvements. This effort to compile all obsidian sourcing data into a central repository is a great use case for archaeological applications of git, which was designed so that content may be easily expanded, to encourage greater collaboration among researchers, and to enable fact checking and error reporting from knowledgeable members of the community. This poster presentation outlines the implementation of git as it pertains to DObsiSS, and highlights the potential benefits of its wider adoption by archaeologists.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>archaeological research</category>
  <category>multidisciplinarity</category>
  <category>archaeological data</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-08-03-github-for-archaeological-databases.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Archaeology and the Anthropocene</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-04-02-archaeology-and-the-anthropocene/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>I’ve been hearing bits and pieces about a concept called the anthropocene, a proposed geological epoch that marks the span in which humans have substantially impacted the environment. According to wikipedia the term was coined in the mid 1980s, but it seems to have caught on among geologists and climate scientists in light of all the evidence pointing towards human involvement in global warming and climate change. While we can definitely say that we live in the anthropocene today, the beginning point of this era is open-ended. There are those who believe that the anthropocene began during the mid 19th century with european industrialization, but other stances assert that the starting point should be pushed back 2000 years ago under the reasoning that some of the largest empires recognized by climate scientists sprang up around this time, or even 15,000 years ago when humans began to dabble with plant domestication and the construction of architecture. Arguments can be made to some degree for all of these propositions, <strong>but what I’m really peeved about is the fact that no archaeologists, anthropologists, historians or classicists are getting substantially involved.</strong> </p>
<p>Last week an article was published in the newly minted journal <em>The Anthropocene Review</em> titled <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/2053019613514953">The technofossil record of humans</a>. Here’s the abstract:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As humans have colonised and modified the Earth’s surface, they have developed progressively more sophisticated tools and technologies. These underpin a new kind of stratigraphy, that we term technostratigraphy, marked by the geologically accelerated evolution and diversification of technofossils –– the preservable material remains of the technosphere <span class="citation" data-cites="haff2014">(Haff 2014)</span>, driven by human purpose and transmitted cultural memory, and with the dynamics of an emergent system. The technosphere, present in some form for most of the Quaternary, shows several thresholds. Its expansion and transcontinental synchronisation in the mid 20th century has produced a global technostratigraphy that combines very high time-resolution, great geometrical complexity and wide (including transplanetary) extent. Technostratigraphy can help characterise the deposits of a potential Anthropocene Epoch and its emergence marks a step change in planetary mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To any archaeologists this may seem a bit bizarro. It seems like the authors are simply switching out terms for ones that fit a common theme. Here’s a breakdown:</p>
<p>Technofossil = Artefact<br>
Technostratigraphy = Assemblage<br>
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/SP395.4">Technosphere</a> = Society</p>
<p><a href="bizarro.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-04-02-archaeology-and-the-anthropocene/bizarro.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>While I am not against the integration of archaeological perspectives within geologic- or atmospheric-based research, I am a bit amazed that the authors of this paper aren’t aware of much of the effort to investigate human-landscape interaction in the social sciences over the last few decades. I’m pretty sure the main participants in the anthropocene discussion are geologists, palaeontologists or climate scientists whose primary focus is the environment itself, but when discussing human processes that may have had a substantial impact don’t you think it would be wise to call upon the already-extensive base of knowledge devised by specialists devoted to this field of research?</p>
<p>But what about the lack of effort made by archaeologists? We complain about hyper-specialization, lack of public engagement and troubles on the job market, but here is a new field wanting to implement the ideas that we take for granted. Not only can we introduce a fresh perspective to this emerging field, but this kind of research is actually on people’s minds. News about climate change, including evidence for it in antiquity, is all over the place, reported by major outlets and smaller blogs alike. There may even be potential for archaeological research to be cited in parliamentary debates!</p>
<p>Essentially, what I’m saying is that there are reasons to involve archaeological research in discussions surrounding the anthropocene that would benefit all parties. Moreover, what’s stopping classicists or historians from getting involved as well? Why not try to establish ourselves more firmly in other fields of research that touches upon our own?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>MA thesis</category>
  <category>github</category>
  <category>open accessdatabase stuff</category>
  <category>anthropocene</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-04-02-archaeology-and-the-anthropocene/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Git as I go</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-02-27-git-as-i-go.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Over the past few weeks I’ve been getting acquainted with git, a version control mechanism that allows users to share code, text or other editable media in a collaborative environment. I’m learning that Github is a great venue for hosting text-based datasets and disseminating preliminary results in a comfortable way.</p>
<p>I’ve always been an advocate for open access to data and I had considered various options for storing and disseminating the database that I am constructing for my Master’s thesis. I really like text-based solutions since they are easy to modify across virtually any platform, they are easily convertible to more complex file formats, and there is a general air of simplicity when working with them. (I now use TextEdit as my primary word processor, switching over to word only whenever I need to do some advanced formatting or track changes.) Now, while I am using FileMaker to enter my data and Excel as a file-conversion intermediary, I am working on transforming my dataset to JSON and its spinoff dialects, geoJSON and bibJSON in particular. JSON is readable by both humans and computers, enabling easy modifications and additions of new data, with versatile ways of displaying and disseminating the information being stored.</p>
<p>Github makes it very easy to read JSON and many other text-based file formats, including tabular data files. Github has even integrated the <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/mapping-geojson-files-on-github#styling-markers">Leaflet</a> mapping tool so geoJSON data can be perused cartographically. I also like Github because it generates stable links for easy sharing, my data can be used by others with similar or widely different goals, and the effort that I put into the collation of this data can be fully recognized, and even expanded upon. However, Github was never intended to be a database-sharing platform and there are some limitations for this kind of use. It would be great if bibliographic entries could be generated so others can cite my work appropriately. Additionally, an option for some form of storage designed for longevity would better suit the goals of academics. Maybe there will be a push in this direction now that <a href="http://blogs.plos.org/everyone/2014/02/24/plos-new-data-policy-public-access-data/">PLOS has updated their open data policy</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve also started to push some of my preliminary analyses to Github as I work on them. Working transparently definitely impacts my mindset since I am encouraged to produce more meaningful results, stay organized, and participate with others doing similar things. I get to show off a bit too, extending my visibility to people at a distance. However saying something meaningful about the results I obtain is the other side of the coin that I must not forget about.</p>
<p>In general, I think this is a good direction for me. It feels great to get my work out there, even in an incomplete state.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>git</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2014-02-27-git-as-i-go.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tubes by Andrew Blum</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-26-tubes-by-andrew-blum.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p><em>Tubes</em> by Andrew Blum is an interesting book (primarily geared towards non-academics) about the physicality of the internet. People tend to participate in the world wide web without considering the fact that the internet is based upon tangible infrastructure. It is indeed a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_cZC67wXUTs">series of tubes</a>&nbsp;through which we communicate, socialize, trade and interact with distant parts of the world. Because of the great things that this heightened connectivity brings us, it is easy to get caught up in the relational aspects as a general user. Blum’s tour of the internet as a device of human construction really brings to light the forces that make it all possible. While his primary focus is to <em>find</em> the internet — to explore it as one would traverse a continent — he accomplishes much more than that. Blum also provides a great overview of the economic and social aspects that make the internet tick.</p>
<p>I feel as though Tubes deals with many issues that archaeologists using network analysis face as well. Scattered archaeological evidence indicates that mechanisms for exchange existed. Presumably artefacts and ideas other than what is manifested in the archaeological record traversed the area alongside these physical objects. In one sense, networks based on the distribution of artefacts are reconstructed in order to raise the possibility that they acted as conduits for broader interaction. From another perspective, networks based on hypothetical models may emphasize the potential for connections to occur with variable weight, and archaeological material may be used as guides for setting values to the parameters set forth under the model. So two clear ways of conducting archaeological network analysis are described briefly here, but one thing is clear: the interplay between the physical manifestations of what archaeologists twist into networks and the social, economic and geographical factors that fostered connectivity is a crucial aspect to each mode of thought. In a very similar vein, Andrew Blum highlights the economic, social and geographical variables that underpin the entire system, and he synthesizes them all to characterize the structure and complexity of the system as a whole.</p>
<p>Blum also recognizes that whether or not users of the internet understand the inner workings of the system that directs many aspects of their lives, it still plays a major role. The western world is much more connected through the internet than the global south, and the lack of even participation may prove to be detrimental. The distribution of connections that form the internet immensely influences entire populations, and even alters our perceptions of world around us. Moreover the network is dynamic, following economic and socio-cultural fluctuations — the ways that these forces change over time may have profound effects on the electronic linkages that form. Again, a striking similarity between the topics that Blum covers and archaeological network analysis is apparent. While prehistoric travellers and traders may not have recognized the extent of the networks that they traversed, the paths that they followed, perhaps influenced by social-cultural or economic concerns, influenced where they would end up and what kinds of information crossed their paths.</p>
<p>I guess I don’t really have any specific point to make here, except to draw attention to how these issues that archaeologists face are being addressed by Blum in an interesting way. However I do think that archaeologists should consider deeper integration between network analysis and geography-oriented methodologies, since the data that we look at tends to be geographical in nature — the distribution of artefacts is often used as the basis networks constructed from archaeological material, and physical distance or elevation data are often considered important variables within interaction models. I singled out geography as an area in need of more focus, but as mentioned above I consider economic or social processes as crucial elements to account for as well. However, geographical data is relatively easy to collect, can be quantified and neatly organized into digital databases, and can be analyzed using already-developed tools, whereas social and economic considerations are often inferred from careful analysis and interpretation of manifestations in the archaeological record. In any case, it is important to develop frameworks that will enable these different-yet-complementary facets of archaeological (and related) networks to be integrated. These considerations are measured in different ways, are analyzed differently, and are discussed differently, but it is necessary to bridge these gaps carefully and explicitly in order to stitch them together effectively. I think that the development of such a framework, perhaps in the form of a set of guidelines or questions that are important to consider, should be a main priority in the coming years as interest in these fields continues to expand.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>archaeological networks</category>
  <category>series of tubes</category>
  <category>the internet</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-26-tubes-by-andrew-blum.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sci-fi and antiquity</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-17-sci-fi-and-antiquity.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>As an avid watcher of sci-fi, and as a student of antiquity, I like to think about how others view the past, the present and the future. Science fiction, which is often co-labelled as speculative fiction, is an avenue for presenting the author’s view of the world under different circumstances. A writer’s view of the future is shaped by his outlook on the world, his attitudes towards broader aspects of his culture, and his interpretation of the past. Similarly, historians write their histories from a certain perspective, which is built up by their own personal experiences, their cultural context, and the academic traditions that have sculpted their interests. I was speaking with a friend about the similarities between the production of science fiction and the study of antiquity, and I want to share some aspects of our discussion and the thoughts that spun off from it.</p>
<p>L and I were discussing this side-project I’m working on that I’m really excited about. I want to write an epic story that occurs in a post-Iliad setting, along the same timeline as The Odyssey, The Aeneid, and the major dramas of the Classical Period of Greece. I also want to incorporate an archaeological spin, tying up the storyline to what is evident today in the archaeological record. I don’t want to reveal too much just yet, I’ll post some more about this later as it develops. The fact that people have been telling these epic stories for generations amazes me, as it’s a way of escaping the contemporary world and situating oneself with the legendary kings of the Aegean, the gods of Olympus, and the adventures that ensued. Among the citizens of Classical Athens, hearing The Iliad being recited must have given a very amazing take on the past; conflicts between polities, military commanders leading armies to war, long journeys interspersed with hazards and oddities along the way. Sounds a lot like Star Trek, doesn’t it?</p>
<p>It also gave ordinary citizens the ability to step into the shoes of the main characters. One could see how a great king would take control of his troops, deal with the interventions of the gods, and tackle the issues that lie in his way. Additionally, there are a few&nbsp;instances when the role of the individual citizen is examined. As an example, the common soldier Thersites, described as the ugliest man who came to Troy, criticized Agamemnon’s leadership and is exemplified as a fool for doing so. Battle scenes are also very illustrative as microcosms for everyday life. By depicting the actions of common men in a certain light, and highlighting possible consequences, these stories associate certain attitudes to various behaviours.</p>
<p>Now, when retelling the innovations of the Classical Period in Athens, scholars base their views on generations of built-up attitudes towards these periods that have accumulated over centuries. We emphasize the roles of the major politicians and tyrants as if we fully understand their ultimate goals and their decision-making processes. However we only understand a certain aspect of their lives. By writing fictional accounts of these characters, with a strong base in our current understandings, we can explore different facets of their lives and consider how they would act in certain novel situations. The author can feel free to invent new characters, develop original story lines or even transpose an entire genre. The developments would reflect the author’s interpretations, and if I was writing I would try to base it in our current understandings as much as possible. I would experiment and see how our view, formed over 2000 years of experience in between, complements my own understanding of this character and of this setting.</p>
<p>Essentially, you could call this fan fiction, and this is certainly not meant in a negative way. By repositioning our understanding of the past, and by extending our own perspectives in a creative, perhaps even playful way, it is possible to get a more <em>real</em> view on a setting of personal interest.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-17-sci-fi-and-antiquity.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using Library Box and Raspberry Pi to implement single-purpose reading workstations</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-17-using-library-box-and-raspberry-pi-to-implement-single-purpose-reading-workstations.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>Earlier this week I wrote about the potential of stepping back from the internet, moving back towards a more functionalist computing environment. That’s not to say that we should inhibit linkages between computers. I’ve been reading about the Pirate Box, as well as it’s fork Library Box, and I think that these devices represent a big step towards better support of scaled back network systems. These devices, developed using open source technology, generate networks that allow connected members to share files and interact, without connecting to the internet at large. Of course, any home or office network has these capabilities, the focus on the functionality of a single main feature breeds novel ideas regarding its implementation.</p>
<p>Drawing on Library Box’s potential on university campuses, I can imagine a network of single purpose devices being utilized in order to aid research efforts. Perhaps in a library setting raspberry pi computers can be set up along with inexpensive sets of periphery devices (monitor, mouse, keyboard), and the only software installed being reading software and a very simple text-editor. These devices would solely be used to retrieve files from a Library Box, read them, and take notes. That’s it. Single purpose device such as these would reduce distractions and enable students to focus on their work.</p>
<p>Such a network is doable, and moreover it is incredibly cheap to implement. The cost of a raspberry pi device is 25$ or 35$, depending on which model is used. Mice are also quite cheap, and monitors may be allocated through donations or partnerships with hardware manufacturers. Depending on the size of the network, multiple Library Boxes may be required, but such a project may be scaled over a long period of time, spreading the costs over a few years. Additionally, it would be encouraged to utilize free, libre and open source software (FLOSS) in the spirit of the Pirate Box’s origins.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-12-17-using-library-box-and-raspberry-pi-to-implement-single-purpose-reading-workstations.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sleep day</title>
  <dc:creator>Zack Batist</dc:creator>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-05-05-sleep-day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
  <div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
    <div class="callout-icon-container">
      <i class="callout-icon"></i>
    </div>
    <div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
      Note
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
    <p>This is an old post and is probably extremely cringe. Please understand that I have moved on from these ideas. Still, it may contain some nuggets that point to some continuity in my thinking over the years, which is why I decided to post it here.</p>
  </div>
</div>




<p>After a long week with little sleep, followed by a night out with friends, I decided that today would be a sleep day. I didn’t set an alarm, I got up late, and I took my time.</p>
<p>Throughout the day I received no emails, no text messages, no spammy newsletters, and no other kinds of notifications. It’s amazing that I find this strange. I never realized how much stress is caused by those little red bubbles telling me that something needs my attention, or that I have to respond to whoever is on the other end. Don’t get me wrong, I want to interact with friends and be up to date on various activities, but it’s important to tune all of that out once in a while.</p>
<p>I’m glad that my sleep day went beyond just turning off my alarm. It’s funny how things work out that way.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/old-posts/2013-05-05-sleep-day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
